<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Prophecies of a white king of Brittaine taken out of the library of Sir Robert Cotton : that most famous antiquary of England in the Saxon character.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3679</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12205628</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12205628</idno>
            <idno type="VID">197263</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28426)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 197263)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 245:E102, no 20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Prophecies of a white king of Brittaine taken out of the library of Sir Robert Cotton : that most famous antiquary of England in the Saxon character.</title>
                  <author>Cotton, Robert, Sir, 1571-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 4, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G. Linsey ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"In tempore Edw. 4th. The Latine of the ensuing English is to be seene in Sir Robert Cottons Library, ... " cf. p. 5 of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:197263:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PROPHECIE OF A White KING of BRITTAINE. TAKEN Out of the Library of Sir <hi>Robert Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> that moſt famous Antiquary of <hi>England,</hi> in the Saxon Character.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>G. Linſey,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop againſt <hi>London-Stone.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:197263:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:197263:2"/>
            <head>THE VVhite KINGS PROPHECIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen ſo Lyon of Rightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is dead, there ſhall riſe a white King in <hi>Brittaine,</hi> firſt Flying, and after Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, after Ligging down; and in this ligge down he ſhal be lymed, after that he ſhall be led. And there ſhall be ſhewed whether there be an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther King: Then ſhall be gadred togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der much folke, and he ſhall take helpe for him: And then there ſhall be Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandice of men, (as of an Horſe, or an
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:197263:3"/> Oxe: And there ſhall be ſought helpe, and there ſhall none ariſe, but bed for head: And then ſhall one gone, there the Sunne ariſeth, another there the Sunne gone downe: After this, it ſhal be ſaid by <hi>Brittaine</hi> (King is King) King is no King. After this he ſhall raiſe up his head, (and he ſhall be taken him to be a king, be many things to done, But wiſe men Reading, And then ſhall a range of Gleeds, and that ever each hath beraveing) he ſhall have it for his owne, And this ſhall laſt ſeven yeeres, Loe raveing and ſhedding of blood: And Ovens ſhall be made like kyrkes, And that as one ſowes another ſhall reape, and death ſhall be better then wretched life, and Charity ſhall be of few men; After then ſhall come through the South with the Sunne, on Horſe of tree, and upon all waves on the Sea, the Chicken of the Eagle ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into <hi>Brittaine,</hi> and arriving anon, to the houſe of the Eagle, he ſhall ſhew
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:197263:3"/> fellowſhip to them beaſts. After a yeere and a halfe ſhall be warre in <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> then ſhall a ſooth be naught worth, and every man ſhall keepe his thing, and gotten other mens good; after the white king feeble ſhall goe towards the Weſt, betlipped about with his folke, to the old place been running water, then his enemies ſhall meet him, and march in her place ſhall be ordained about him in Hoaſt, on the manner of a ſhield ſhall be formed, then ſhall they fighten on Oven front, After the white king ſhall fall into a kirke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard over a Hall. After the Chicken of the Eagle ſhall neſtle in the higheſt Rooch of all <hi>Brittaine,</hi> nay he ſhall naught be ſlaine young: nay he naught come old, for then the Gentile worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhall naught ſuffer wrong be done to him, But when the Reame is in peace then ſhall he die, and two yeeres after ſhall come a new Rule from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and ſetle holy kirke as hit ſhall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:197263:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:197263:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:197263:5"/> ever more ſtand, and bring three Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries into one, <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> unto the day of doome and the holy Croſſe be brought into Chriſtian mens hands, and there ſhall be made a Temple that never was made, ſuch none.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Originall hereof was found by the Lady <hi>Poſton</hi> of the County of Norfolke, amongſt the evidences of <hi>Edw.</hi> the fourth his time.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:197263:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IN Tempore</hi> EDW. 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. The Latine of this enſuing Engliſh is to be ſeene in Sir <hi>Robert Cottons</hi> Library, that famous Antiquary of <hi>England,</hi> in the Saxon Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, the ſtyle of the Latine and this Engliſh fitly ſuiting that ancient tone.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
